<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications | UEA MED Genomic Pipelines</title>
    <link>/publication/</link>
      <atom:link href="/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Publications</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_huae0f1a26bea34e0d96985e34aa3de8bd_277_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/publication/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Germline variant caller</title>
      <link>/publication/germline_variant/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/germline_variant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After samples have passed QC and have been mapped, samples can be analysed using our germline variant pipeline - both exome and whole genome sequencing (WGS). For familial based analysis, pedigree (PED) files can also be supplied to allow overlaps between affected/unaffected family members. The germline variant pipeline is composed of 3 main parts; the first 2 parts analyses files using 2 independent variant callers; GATK Haplotype caller and Freebayes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both GATK and the Freebayes submodule of the pipeline were created in-house. The GATK module includes all the reccomennded tools described from the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gatk.broadinstitute.org/hc/en-us/articles/360035535932-Germline-short-variant-discovery-SNPs-Indels-&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Germline short variant discovery (SNPs + Indels workflow)&lt;/a&gt;. This module automates 11 processes including recalibration against known common variants, variant calling (HaplotypeCaller), convolutional neural network variant scoring and filtering  to produce a list of high quality variants. In contrast, the Freebayes module utilises a bayesian  approach which then filters variants based on quality scores and depth (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ekg/freebayes)&#34;&gt;https://github.com/ekg/freebayes)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Somatic variant caller</title>
      <link>/publication/somatic_variant/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/somatic_variant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;signature.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure - mutational signature analysis from Tumoroid cancer project&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After samples have passed QC and have been mapped, tumor-normal matched samples can be analysed using our somatic variant pipeline - both exome and whole genome sequencing (WGS) is supported with these pipelines.. This pipeline is composed of 3 main parts; the first 2 parts analyses files using 2 independent variant callers from Sanger and GATK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sanger pipelines cgpWXS and cgpWGS were designed for exome and WGS, respectively (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cancerit)&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cancerit)&lt;/a&gt;. Both Sanger pipelines utilise CAVeMAN and Pindel to call single base substitutions (SBSs) and insertions-deletions (indels) which are annotated by VAGrENT. CgpWGS also includes BRASS and ascatNgs for breakpoint and copy number analysis. Both tools identify high quality variants that are used downstream for further analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GATK pipeline was developed in-house and include all the reccomennded tools described in the the  
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gatk.broadinstitute.org/hc/en-us/articles/360035889791--How-to-Call-somatic-mutations-using-GATK4-Mutect2-Deprecated-&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mutect2 GATK workflow&lt;/a&gt;. This pipeline automates 10 processes including recalibration against known common variants, variant calling (mutect2), contamination calculation and filtering variants to produce a list of high quality variants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final part of our pipeline creates an overlap between the variants found in both Sanger and GATK variant callers. A html report is created from the results that includes annotated variants significantly different between normal and tumor samples, variant class summary (E.g. nosense, stop codon, etc) across samples, cancer drug prediction and variant allele frequencies - an example of this is shown in the colorectal cancer tumoroid project [here](put inthe hhtps when ready)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variant QC Pipeline</title>
      <link>/publication/qc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/qc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;fastqc.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the sequencing of samples, it is always essential to perform quality control (QC) steps prior to the main analysis - a number of sequencing artefacts including read errors, adaptor/primer retention and low quality read contamination is quite common in sequencing experiments. Sequencing errors can impact  downstream analyses of samples including gene expression and single base substitutions and insertions-deletions (indels) calling. The majority of these downstream analyses do not perform filtering steps or provide tools for QC, therefore these sequencing artefacts are required to be filtered out to prevent inaccurate results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;QC_pipeline.png&#34; alt=&#34;figure 1 - QC pipeline flowchart &#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have developed pipelines that include the all the essential QC tools for both RNA and DNA (variant exome and WGS) sequencing experiments - summarised in figure 1. Irrespective of sample type, samples are first trimmed using TrimGalore, analysed by FastQC and aligned (cgpMAP and HISAT2 for DNA and RNA, respectively). The picard toolkit suite is also used to remove PCR and optical duplicates, give read insert sizes and alignment statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional tools have been included to estimate the levels of contamination (verifyBAMID), relatedness scores and ancestry estimation in DNA-seq samples (Somalier) - shown in figure 2. These analsyes allow the identification of samples that may have been mislabelled, contaminated or degraded thus preventing errouneous result interepretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once all analyses have been performed, multiQC is used to create QC plots reporting results in an easy and digestible format. An example of a multiQC report is shown below (for a fully interactive html report click here)!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PUT IN MUTLIQC REPORT !!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
